(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-13T02:34:49.739393",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.6-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
しくじりかなたそ 僕みたいになるなー！
"Blundering Kanataso: Don't become like me!"
イエーイ！
Yay!
はい、ということで、担任天音かなたです。よろしくお願いします！
Alright! I'm your homeroom teacher, Amane Kanata. Pleased to meet you!
よろしくお願いします！
Pleased to meet you!
それでは生徒の皆さんの自己紹介を。
Now then, let's have self-introductions from the students.
はーい。モグモグおかゆー、ホロライブゲーマーズの猫又おかゆです。よろしくお願いします、先生。
Present! Mogu mogu Okayu, I'm Nekomata Okayu from hololive GAMERS. Nice to meet you, teacher!
はい！そしてラミちゃん！
Yes! Next up, Lamy-chan!
はーい！ホロライブ5期生の顔が肝臓、雪花ラミィです。かな先生、よろしくお願いします！
Present! Face of hololive 5th Gen and liver of the team, Yukihana Lamy! Kana-sensei, nice to meet you!
探してリリカちゃん！
And next, Ririka-chan!
はい！先生カワイイ、ポジティブ、ジーニアス、ホロライブデバイスのしくじり担当、一条莉々華でーす！
Present! Cute, positive genius, and in charge of blunders in hololive DEV_IS, Ichijou Ririka here!
そんなことない！大丈夫大丈夫！そんなことない全然！
That's not true! You're completely fine!
本当に皆さん、お忙しい中集まっていただきありがとうございます。
Thank you all so much for gathering here today despite your busy schedules.
こちらこそ！楽しみ！
The pleasure is ours! Looking forward to it!
カニ奢りますから！
I'll treat you all to crab!
やったー！
Yay!
カニをもってお礼とさせていただきますので。
I'll treat you to crab as a token of my gratitude.
ということでね、今日はですね、僕がやってしまった...
So today, I'll be talking...
...過去のしくじりをたくさん話して...
...about my past blunders and mistakes...
...みんな同じことを繰り返さぬように...
...so that none of you repeat the same mistakes...
...これからの活動の参考にしてもらえたらと。
...and hopefully you can use it as reference for your future activities.
早速なんですが、僕のしくじりについて授業を始めていきたいと思います！
Without further ado, I'd like to begin the lesson on my blunders!
それでは皆さん、お手元にある教科書の1ページ目を開いてください。
Now then, everyone, please open to page 1 of your textbook.
はーい！
Okay!
「デビュー直後のキャラ迷走！天音かなたのしくじり人生」
"Losing Character Identity Right After Debut! Amane Kanata's Life of Blunders"
え、でもそんなことあったっけ？
Huh? But did something like that even happen?
あったんですね、実は。
It actually did happen.
じゃあまずは、デビュー直後の天音かなたのホロライブ人生の上がり下がりをグラフにしてみました。
First, I charted out the ups and downs of my Hololive life right after debut.
次のページ！
Next page!
下がってるねー！こんなにー？！
It's going down! By this much?!
そうですね、やっぱりデビューが100だとしたら、だんだん下がっていって50%...
Yeah... if debut was 100%, it gradually went down to 50%...
...まだ1年も経たないうちに20%とかその辺に...
...and before even a year passed, it dropped to around 20%...
急降下しましたね
It dropped sharply, didn't it?
えー、何があったんですか？
What on earth happened?
いや、ちょっと何があったのか解説していきたいと思います。
Well, I'd like to explain what happened.
僕は2019年12月27日、約5年前ですね、デビューしたんですけれども
I debuted on December 27, 2019, about 5 years ago, but...
デビュー前、「これから楽しいホロライブ人生が始まるんだ！」と期待に胸を大きく膨らませていました。
Before my debut, I swelled with high expectations, thinking "A fun Hololive life is starting!"
なんてなんて？そんな平らなのに？
Say what? Even though you're so flat?
ちょっと！
Hey!
膨らみすぎて破裂しちゃっただけですもんね
It just swelled up too much and popped, right?
破裂して、まだ膨らみ続けているという感じなんですが
It popped, and it's still continuing to swell up, but...
デビュー前は憧れの先輩たちに一人一人に全部違う文章で連絡をしました。
Before my debut, I messaged each of my admired seniors with completely unique texts.
くれてた！くれてた！
You did! You did!
おかゆちゃんにも送りましたし、頑張ってデビュー配信の資料を作ったりもしてて。
I sent one to Okayu-chan too, and I worked hard making slides for my debut stream.
みんなデビュー前ってどんな感じでした？
How was everyone before your debut?
莉々華ほんとまだ直近じゃないですか？
Lirika's was really recent, wasn't it?
偉大なる先輩たちの配信をいっぱい見て研究して、3ヶ月～4ヶ月かけてデビュー配信の準備をしました。
I watched and researched lots of streams by my great seniors, taking 3 to 4 months preparing for my debut stream.
すごい！
Amazing!
ラミィもデビューするまでは何ヶ月もかけてデビュー初配信の準備をしてた。
Lamy also spent months preparing for her debut stream before debuting.
おかゆんは？
What about Okayun?
僕の時はその準備とかないからさ。全然もう...
In my time, there was no preparation like that. Not at all...
多少ね、1時間持たせるためにちょっとした工夫はありましたけど
I had a few small tricks to make the hour pass, but...
今の子たちの初配信とはクオリティの差がハンパなかったですよ。
The quality difference compared to today's debut streams was insane.
確かに。どんどんね、初配信ってクオリティが上がっていって
Indeed. Debut streams keep getting higher and higher in quality,
いきなりオリジナル曲があるとか、オープニングにアニメーションがあるとかあったと思うんですけど
like having an original song right away, or an opening animation...
その大事な初配信ではこんなしくじりをしました！次のページ！
In that important debut stream, I made this big mistake! Next page!
パワーポイントで自分を紹介。視聴者の意見はクソダサい！
Introduced myself with PowerPoint. Viewers' opinion: Super tacky!
あったあった～！
Oh yeah, that happened!
一生懸命1ヶ月以上かけて作ったパワーポイントの資料が酷評されてしまいまして...
The PowerPoint slides I spent over a month making were harshly criticized...
そんな僕の初配信の映像がございますので見てほしいです。映像がこちら！
We have footage of my debut stream, so I'd love for you to see it. Here it is!
じゃーん。ようこそ。
Ta-da. Welcome.
何このクソダサの演出？ダサ！
What is this super tacky entrance? So tacky!
星マークえぐ！謎の寿司！何だこの寿司！
The star marks are crazy! Mysterious sushi! What's with this sushi?!
自己紹介をしていきたいと思います。読みづらっ！
I'd like to introduce myself. So hard to read!
夢や目標。登録者数5万人。
Dreams and goals. 50,000 subscribers.
これをね、皆さんホロライブ好きな方は分かると思うんですけど、まず3D化したいってことで5万人をまず目指そうと。
As Hololive fans know, I aimed for 50k to get a 3D model.
ライブに出演してコールアンドレスポンスをやりたい。あれね、ちょっとね、夢ですね。
I want to perform in concerts and do call-and-response. That's a dream of mine.
今のパワーポイントの準備に1ヶ月ガチでかけてます。
I legitimately spent a whole month preparing that PowerPoint.
ヤバすぎる！同期にも「その1ヶ月他のことできただろう」とか...
That's crazy! My genmates even told me "You could've done other things in that month"...
色々言われたんですけど、皆さんどうでしたか？おしゃれでした？正直に莉々華どうだった？
They said a lot, but what did you guys think? Was it stylish? Honestly, Lirika, how was it?
くっそダサいです！やっぱダサい？
It's super tacky! Is it really tacky after all?
うん...ダサいかな。それがかなたんの良さだよね。ちょっとダサい。
Yeah... kinda tacky. That's Kanatan's charm though. A bit tacky.
個性はあったよね。PP天使とか言われてたしね。
It had personality. You were called PP Angel and all.
未だに海外ニキはPPエンジェルって言ってくれたり... Tシャツもありますもんね、最初に出したやつね。
Overseas fans still call me PP Angel... And there's even a T-shirt, the first one I released.
しかもデビュー配信では他にも全部自分の声で演奏から作ったソーラン節を流したりと、尖ったデビュー配信をね、かませねばとやっておりましたが...
Plus, in my debut stream, I played Soran Bushi made entirely from my own voice instrumentals, trying to deliver an edgy debut stream...
ソーラン節ってなんですか？ソーラン節ね！見たいですか？見たい！映像があるのでご覧ください！
What is Soran Bushi? Soran Bushi! Do you want to see it? Yes! Here's the video, please take a look!
いらすとやさんも使用してますからね。ちゃんとコールも黄色くなってて...
You even used Irasutoya graphics! The chant text is highlighted in yellow too...
みんなが言うところもあるんだ。
There's even a part for everyone to join in.
すごい！低音も高音も聞こえる！いっぱいいる！
Awesome! You can hear both low and high pitch! There are so many of you!
エコーかかってる！ぼふぼふのエコーかかってますね。
There's echo! It's got a muffled echo going on.
右上を見ていただくと、みんな「ドッコイショ」って言ってる... 最後のドヤ顔ね！
If you look at the top right, everyone's saying "Dokkoisho"... That smug face at the end!
やかんやん！やかん...
It sounds like a kettle! Kettle...
こんな配信をしておりますがね、実は初めはクールキャラで行こうと考えて...
I did such a stream, but actually at first I was planning to go with a cool character...
それで、そう。
So, yeah...
やっぱり参考にしていたのは、おかゆ先輩。
the one I was referencing was Okayu-senpai.
これは本当に...
This is really...
間違いでなくね。
No mistake, you know.
いや〜ありがたいね。
Wow, I'm grateful.
ね？
Right?
いや、もう本当にね、あの...
Yeah, well, really, um...
まぁ、クールぶっていたけど、なんかダサいらしいパワーポイントを駆使してね...
While I tried to act cool, using a somewhat uncool PowerPoint presentation...
今後の迷走を予感させる配信となってしまいました。
my stream ended up forecasting my future wandering.
でもみんなも初配信はあるということで、皆さんどうですか？自分の初配信、
But since everyone has a debut stream, how about you all? Do you...
覚えてますか？おかゆ先輩。
remember your own debut stream, Okayu-senpai?
覚えてますよ。
I remember it.
おっ！
Oh!
まあ、若かった。
Well, I was young.
今も若いですよ！
You're still young!
今も若い！
Still young!
もう7年目かな？
Is it my 7th year already?
7年の経過と思うと、まぁそれはね、確かに時間が経って大人になっている感...
Thinking about 7 years passing, well, that certainly feels like becoming an adult over time...
それは感じろかな。
I do feel that.
そう。デビュー配信もね、僕も終わり、ダサいと言われつつも...
Yeah. As for my debut stream, even though I was called uncool...
1週間後に、あの先ほど夢で掲げました、登録者5万人を達成し、
one week later, I reached the 50,000 subscribers I aimed for in my dream...
出だしは非常に順調だったんですが...
So the start was extremely smooth, but...
僕はこちらの気持ちを抱くようになります。次のページ！
I started to feel like this. Next page!
プレッシャーだな...
"The pressure is real..."
わかるー！
I totally get that!
プレッシャーだー。
"So much pressure..."
やっぱり、あの、hololiveというところに所属させていただいたことによる...
After all, belonging to hololive...
リスナーさん、数字とかってあったので、
brought listeners and numbers to worry about, so...
特に、その、デビューして何もしてないから、「いいのかな？これで」っていうのを感じたりしましたね。
especially since I hadn't done anything yet right after debut, I felt like, "Is this really okay?"
皆さんはこう、デビューしたての時ってどうでしたか？
How was it for you all when you just debuted?
ラミィは、もう、それこそ4期生が盛り上がってるところでデビューをしたので、
For me, I debuted right when Gen 4 was booming, so...
プレッシャーもすごかったし、
the pressure was huge,
結構、批判的な意見も多かった。
and there were a lot of critical comments too.
え、そうなの？
Huh, really?
どんな？
Like what?
いや、もう...「ゴキブリの5期生」とか...
Well... things like "Gen 5 cockroach"...
ええ〜っ！！
What?!
ひどいよ！
That's terrible!
結構「才能なし」みたいな...
And stuff like "talentless"...
ええ〜っ！！
What?!
すごい言われましたよ。
I was told all kinds of things.
でもやっぱり、こう、先輩が築き上げてきたものに乗っかってる感じだったので...
But it really felt like we were just riding on what our seniors had built up, so...
気持ちはわかる。
I get how you felt.
そう、プレッシャーがすごかった。
Yeah, the pressure was intense.
ええ〜っ！
Wow...
おかゆ先輩はありました？プレッシャー。
Did you have any pressure, Okayu-senpai?
いや、僕が入った時は、もう、そんなね、
Well, back when I joined,
まだまだ人も少なくて...
there weren't that many people yet...
もう、「大空スバル選手権」の前日に、
So the day before the "Oozora Subaru Championship,"
大空スバルのモノマネの練習をするだけで1時間枠取ったり...
I literally took a whole hour-long stream just practicing doing impressions of Oozora Subaru!
プレッシャー感じなくていいから、マジで！
Seriously, there's no need to feel pressure from that!
いいな〜！古き良きホロライブを感じますね。
Nice! It really gives that good old Hololive vibe.
そんなこともありますよ。
Things like that happened back then.
そうだね。僕もね、やっぱりデビュー直後だったので、特にね、
True. For me, right after debut, especially...
先輩たちにも何か恩返ししたいとか、リスナーさんにも何かとか、そういうことをすごく考えていました。
I was constantly thinking about wanting to give back to my seniors, or doing something for the listeners.
そして、この考えが悪い方に働いてしまい、その結果、僕はこうなってしまいます！
And this mindset worked against me, resulting in me turning into this!
ええ〜っ！？
What?!
次のページ！
Next page!
デビュー直後のキャラ迷走、気合いが完全に空回りしていた、暗黒の「初期かなた」時代！
Character identity crisis right after debut! Overenthusiasm completely backfiring! The dark "Early Kanata" era!
うわ〜！暗黒ですか？
Woah! "Dark"?
暗黒...
Dark...
もうとんでもない暗黒の時代でした。
It was an insanely dark period.
初期かなたがどんな感じだったのか...
As for what "Early Kanata" was like...
デビュー当時の状況を説明しますと...
to explain the situation at the time of my debut...
当時は『ARK』というゲームが大流行しておりましてね。
At the time, a game called "ARK" was immensely popular.
流行ってた！みんなやってたもんね！
It was so popular! Everyone was playing it!
で、僕はゲームに慣れていなかったので、
And since I wasn't used to gaming,
まぁゲームもワタワタしつつ、コラボも喋りも頑張って、でもコメントも拾わなきゃと、全部やろうとしたら...
while flustering over the game, trying hard to handle collabs and talking, while also picking up comments—trying to do everything...
先輩が喋ってるのにコメントを読んだりとか...
I would read comments while my seniors were speaking...
空気が読めていない「初期かなた」が誕生してしまったと。
resulting in the birth of the room-deaf "Early Kanata."
本当にね...
Truly...
ガムシャラすぎて、焦りから異常に空気が読めてないのに、無駄に積極的に話しかけてくる「だる絡みの初期かなた」。
Being overly reckless and anxious made me insanely oblivious to the mood, yet aggressively talking to people—an annoying "Early Kanata."
これね、結構ね、見てたんだけど...
I... I actually watched those streams...
本当ですか？
Really?
まぁ、ちょっと苦しくなる...胸がキュッてなる...
Well... it kind of makes you cringe... Makes your heart tighten...
ちょっと、あの共感性羞恥と、悪意がないのはたぶん伝わるので、キュッとなる系ではありますね。
It gives second-hand embarrassment, though you can tell there's no malice, so it definitely makes your heart tighten.
頑張ろうとしてた感じがね。
You could tell she was trying hard.
ですね。
Right.
おかゆ先輩、初期かなた時代の僕って覚えてますか？
Okayu-senpai, do you remember me from the "Early Kanata" era?
いや、僕、実はARKって1回ぐらいしか参加してないから...
Well, to be honest, I only participated in ARK like once, so...
配信中のかなたんより、配信してないかなたんと関わる方が多かったんですよ。
I actually interacted more with off-stream Kanatan than on-stream Kanatan.
ああ、なるほど！
Ah, I see!
だから配信してないかなたんは、今とあんまり変わんないと思う。
So off-stream Kanatan didn't really seem any different from how she is now.
そうなんです！実は配信外では普通だったので...
Exactly! Off-stream I was totally normal, so...
なんで配信中はこんなおかしくて、裏では普通に話せるのに、「あなた何でなの？」っていうのをホロメンに言われたこともありました。
hololive members even asked me, "Why are you so weird on stream when you can talk normally off-stream?"
「何でそんなおかしくなっちゃうねん」っていうね。
Like, "Why do you get like that?"
まぁでも、初期かなたを見たリスナーの反応はと言うと...
But anyway, as for the listeners' reactions to Early Kanata...
怖いよ...
I'm scared...
次のページ！
Next page!
「推しに絡まないで欲しい」「早く辞めろ」
"Don't bother my fave!" "Quit already!"
ねえ。もちろん応援してくれる人もたくさんいたんですけど...
Right? Of course, there were plenty of people supporting me too, but...
実はこれ、配信開始をする前、待機所の状態でコメントが大荒れしたこともあって...
before the stream even started, while in the waiting room, the chat would get completely wild...
ええ〜っ！？
What?!
500人ぐらいの人がずっと言い合いをする...
Like 500 people arguing with each other non-stop...
こともあるほど、やっぱりリスナーさんからちょっと嫌われてる時期ありましたね。
...to the point where there was a period when listeners kind of disliked me.
あ〜、そうなんだ。
Ah, really?
今じゃ考えられないけど...
That's unthinkable now, though...
いやいや、そんなことないんですけど、具体的にね、どんな感じだったかと言いますと...
No, no, that's not true, but if I were to explain how it specifically was...
コラボの流れをぶった切ってコメントを読んでしまう...
Interrupting the flow of the collab to read comments...
面白いこと言わなきゃ言わなきゃとして、しゃべりまくる...
Chattering non-stop out of an urge to say something funny...
コラボ相手のオウム返しをしてしまう...
Parrot-repeating what my collab partners said...
これがね、結構多かった。
This was happening quite a lot.
オウム返しも焦りから「何か言わなきゃ」...
The parrot-repeating also came from panicking, thinking "I have to say something"...
「沈黙を作らないように」っていうのが...
...and "I mustn't let there be silence"...
たぶん焦りすぎてね、悪循環になってしまったと。
I guess panicking too much turned into a vicious cycle.
いうことがありましたね。これはもう初期かなた。
That's what happened. This was early-days Kanata.
本当に大きなしくじりなんですが...
It was a really big mistake, but...
みんなは新人時代の自分を振り返ってみて、どうですか？
...how about you guys when you look back on your newbie days?
うぅ... / 手が震えてる！
Ugh... / Her hands are trembling!
ラミィはね、やっぱり初期ラミィをいじられるほど、初期とキャラが変わってるので...
For me, since my character has changed so much that my early self gets teased...
ちょっと昔のラミィを思い出してみるだけで、「うぅ...」ってなるんですけど...
Just remembering the old Lamy makes me go "Ugh...", but...
やっぱこう、求められる像にならなきゃ、みたいな...
I felt like I had to become the image people expected of me...
「リスナーさんがこんなラミィを求めてるだろう」みたいのに...
Thinking, "The listeners probably want this kind of Lamy"...
応えようとして、ああなっていった、みたいな...
...and trying to live up to that turned me into that person...
「hololiveは清楚を求めている」みたいなね。 / ああ〜なるほどね！
Like "hololive demands purity." / Ah, I see!
莉々華はちょっと前のことだけど、変わったって思うことある？
Ririka, it was just a little while ago for you, but do you feel like you've changed?
いや、もう莉々華、今も現在進行形で、今お話しされてたみたいなことに悩まされてて、もう今帰りたいです！
No, I'm currently going through the exact same struggle you guys just talked about, I just wanna go home right now!
ダメだよ！ダメ！ダメダメダメ！
You can't! No! No, no, no!
いや、でもやっぱ一皮むきたい！頑張りたいです！
But I really want to break out of my shell! I want to try my best!
莉々華、めちゃめちゃいいと思いますよ。
Ririka, I think you're doing amazing as you are.
ま、こんな感じでね、良かれと思って、ま、根は陰キャなのに...
So, like this, thinking I was doing the right thing, even though I'm an introvert at heart...
頑張って先輩たちに話しかけまくって、空回りする僕は...
...I'd aggressively talk to my seniors and end up overdoing it...
自分の精神、素の性格とキャラのズレが大きくなっていきます。
...causing a huge gap between my true personality and my persona, draining my mental state.
そして、自分が表でやっていく上でのキャラクターというか...
And so, the character I presented publicly...
自分の性格に合ったキャラクターに軌道修正することになります。
...had to be course-corrected into one that actually fits my true personality.
なるほど〜！ / はっちゃけキャラ、やめようと。
I see~! / Deciding to quit the hyperactive persona.
結局ね、やっぱりキャラに無理があると精神が削られるんですよね？
After all, forcing a fake persona really wears down your spirit, right?
ね？
Right?
分かります！！！とっても分かります！
I feel you!!! I feel you so much!
ちなみにホロメンとうまく絡めなかったとか、配信後に後悔したようなことを経験がある人いますか？
By the way, is there anyone who experienced regret after a stream, like not being able to interact well with Holo members?
莉々華？ / 全然ないですけどね... なんかそんな...
Ririka? / None at all, really... Nothing like that...
お酒を飲んでね...
I drank some alcohol, and...
すごい後悔して、ラミィ先輩にあの、Discordで...「本当に申し訳ございませんでした」...
...felt terrible regret, so I sent Lamy-senpai a Discord message saying, "I am truly so sorry"...
「よろしければ、また一緒に遊んでいただけると嬉しいです」って...
..."If it's okay, I'd be delighted if we could hang out again"...
つい最近だ！ / つい最近、今年の話ですね！
That was just recently! / That literally happened this year!
そんなこともあって、僕一時期、気持ちがどん底まで落ち続けてしまいましたが...
With things like that happening, my spirits kept sinking to rock bottom for a while...
迷走しながらも配信を頑張って続けることで、プラスの影響が起きていきます！次のページ！
...but by pushing through and continuing streams even while lost, positive changes started happening! Next page!
配信を続ける中で、キャラが定着！ / やった〜！すごい！
As I kept streaming, my character took root! / Yay~! Awesome!
ということでね、長い時間をかけてつきはしましたが...
So, while it did take a long time...
配信の中でできた関係性や、ホロメンにいじってもらって、いい感じでキャラが定着したり...
...the relationships built during streams and getting teased by Holo members helped shape a solid persona...
自分のことをみんなに知ってもらったりして、配信がやりやすくなっていきます。
...and as everyone got to know me better, streaming became much easier.
配信で定着した天音かなたのキャラがこちら！次のページ！
Here is the character of Amane Kanata that settled through streaming! Next page!
センスなしキャラ！握力ゴリラキャラ！ツッコミキャラ！
No-sense character! Gorilla grip character! Straight-man character!
これぞかなたん！ / 今のカナたんだよね！
That's classic Kanatan! / That's the Kanatan of today!
「センスなしキャラ」についてはね、僕はちょっと認めてないんですけど...
As for the "no-sense character", I don't really accept that one myself, but...
認めてないんだ？ / 周りからダサいと言われた代表的なものがたくさんあるんですよ。
You don't accept it? / There are plenty of iconic things people called uncool on me.
PP天使、洋服がダサい...
PPTenshi, uncool clothes...
あとはトレンド入りした「#かなたやめろ」という...
...and "#KanataYamero" (Kanata Stop It) which trended on Twitter...
はい、PP天使は先ほど紹介しましたが、皆さん、僕の「センスなしキャラ」ということで思い当たる節があったりしますか？
Yes, I already introduced PPTenshi earlier, but do any of you have memories of my "no-sense character"?
いや〜、ないよね！？あるっちゃあるというか...
Well... no, right!? Though actually, I guess there is...
一時期ね、かなたんの洋服について話し合うDiscordのグループがあったりとかね...
At one point, there was a Discord group dedicated to discussing Kanatan's fashion choices...
あの、ラミィとミオ先輩とマリンを集めて突然作って...
I suddenly made it by gathering Lamy, Mio-senpai, and Marine...
「僕、洋服がダサいって言われるんで、おしゃれな洋服（ネットで買える）を教えてください」
..."People say my clothes are tacky, so please teach me stylish clothes (that can be bought online)."
外に買いに行かないんだ！ネットで買えるのが大事なんだ！ / 行きたくなかった、という専用のグループがあったりもしましたね。確かに。
Not going out to buy them! Buying online was essential! / I didn't want to go out—so yeah, that group existed too. True.
ちなみにさっき「#かなたやめろ」がトレンド入りしたっておっしゃってたと思うんですけど、あれは一体何なんですか？
By the way, you mentioned earlier that "#KanataYamero" trended. What on earth was that about?
これはですね、僕のメンバーシップの名前を付ける時の話なんだけど、元々名前の候補が3つありまして...
Well, that was when we were deciding the name for my channel membership. Originally, there were 3 candidates...
かなたーず、THEかなた、かなたふぁんくらぶ。
Kanatas, THE Kanata, Kanata Fan Club.
これな〜！可愛いよね！ / これは... まぁ... うん...
Ah, these~! They're cute, right! / Well... um... yeah...
ま、こんな感じで候補がありまして、これを見た...
So yeah, these were the candidates, and when people saw this...
リスナーさんの反応がこちら！
Here are the listeners' reactions!
「全部ダサいってすごい」「ここまで悩むアンケートは初めて」「センスが息をしていない」
"Awesome that all of them are tacky," "Never seen a poll with such hard choices," "Her sense of style isn't breathing"...
ボロクソやん！
They totally trashed it!
厳しいな
That's harsh.
悩んでアンケート入れられないと
Saying they were so torn they couldn't even vote.
ネーミングセンスがダサすぎたということで、この時「#かなたやめろ」のハッシュタグがつけられ、なんと日本のトレンドに入ります
Because my naming sense was so terrible, the hashtag "#KanataStopIt" went viral and actually trended in Japan.
すごーい！
Wow! Amazing!
恥ずかしいな
That's so embarrassing.
おかしいでしょ！でも、どの名前がいいかなって当時のTwitterで投票してもらった結果がこうなります！
Isn't that crazy?! But here are the results of the Twitter poll from back then!
「THEかなた」が選ばれたと
"THE Kanata" was chosen.
全部ほぼ一緒で、みんな悩んでる！
But they're all almost equal, everyone was really struggling!
僅差なの！
It was such a close race!
大接戦の末「THEかなた」に決定したんですよね
After a hard-fought battle, it was decided as "THE Kanata".
悩んだだろうな、これみんな
Everyone must have really struggled with this choice.
みんな悩みましたね
Everyone really struggled with it.
結局、時を経て去年あたりですかね、「THEかなた」がダサいことに私は気づきました
In the end, after some time passed, around last year, I realized that "THE Kanata" was actually tacky.
気づきを得た！
She gained self-awareness!
いろんなみんながおしゃれな名前だったり、ストレートにファンネームをつけているみんなのメンバーシップを見て、「THEかなた」ってダサかったんだと思いまして...
Looking at everyone else having stylish names or using straightforward fan names for their memberships, I realized "THE Kanata" was pretty tacky...
現在のメンバーシップの名前は「へい民」になっております
...so the current membership name has become "Heimin".
よかった〜！
Thank goodness~!
よかったじゃない！ / 拍手すんな！
Isn't that great?! / Don't applaud!
残念だろ！
That's supposed to be disappointing for me!
他にもかなた先輩といえば気になってることがあって、握力キャラというか、力がめっちゃあるみたいな感じで、自己紹介とかでも言ってると思うんですけど、あれは最初からではなかったんですか？
Speaking of Kanata-senpai, there's another thing I was curious about: your grip strength persona. You mention having insane strength in your intros, but was that not there from the start?
自己紹介で言うようになったのは途中からね
I only started saying it in intros partway through.
中学校の頃から握力が強くて、雑談の中で「握力50kgあったんだよね」みたいなことを言ったり...
Ever since middle school, my grip was strong, so I'd mention in streams like, "My grip strength was 50kg,"...
力強くて物が壊れちゃうって話をよくしてたら、だんだん握力ゴリラキャラが定着していって...
...and talking about how things break because of my strength. Eventually, the "Grip Strength Gorilla" persona stuck...
今までうっかり握りつぶしたものはこちらです
...and here are the things I've accidentally crushed so far!
多いなあ！
That's so many!
蒸したジャガイモ、お弁当のスプーン、コーヒーメーカー、キーボード、Switchのコントローラーなどなどですね
Steamed potato, bento spoon, coffee maker, keyboard, Switch controller, and so on.
マカロンを初めて食べた時に優しく持とうと思ったんだけど、優しく持ったのにボロッボロになって...
When I ate a macaron for the first time, I tried to hold it gently, but even so, it crumbled completely into pieces...
そのエピソード大好き！
I love that story!
この中にある「お弁当のスプーン」ってやつなんですけど...
Regarding the "bento box spoon" on this list...
ラミーの企画にかなたんが出た時に、楽屋で出るお弁当がカレーだったんだけど、その時のスプーンをバキッて壊しちゃって...
When Kanatan appeared on my stream project before, the green room bento was curry, and she snapped the spoon right then...
折れたんだよ勝手に！普通に食べてるだけでスプーン壊れてて！
It broke on its own! I was just eating normally and the spoon broke!
びっくりしましたねー
I was so surprised!
家では石のスプーンとか使ってるんですか？
Do you use stone spoons at home or something?
石のスプーン違いますよ！
Stone spoons?! No, I don't!
ちゃんと割り箸とか使いますけど、たまに割り箸も割れるけど...
I properly use disposable chopsticks and stuff, though sometimes those break too...
スプーンまっぷたつ事件は楽屋でこれやったのは2回あります
The spoon-snapping-in-half incident has happened twice in green rooms.
やばーい！
That's crazy!
ちょっと前配信の流れで握力を計測した結果がこちらでございます
A while ago, here is the result when we measured my grip strength during a stream.
え〜〜！？ 55.9kg！？ ゴリラやん！
Ehh?! 55.9kg?! You're a total gorilla!
配信でお酒を珍しく飲んだ時に「酔ってリミッター外れてんじゃない？」みたいなお家にある握力計で測ってみたんですけど、55.9kgの新記録が出まして
When I had a rare drink during a stream, we joked "Are your limiters off because you're drunk?", so I tested with my dynamometer at home, and set a new record of 55.9kg.
レスリングの霊長類最強女子の吉田沙保里さんがあるテレビ番組で計測したのが55kgだった...
Yoshida Saori, the strongest female primate in wrestling, measured 55kg on a TV show...
それ超えてます！
You surpassed her!
ちょっと握手してみます？
Want to try shaking hands?
ラミー前に握手したことあるんで
Lamy has shaken hands with me before.
新人ちゃん！ / 莉々華 握力7kgだったんですけど...
Newbie! / Ririka's grip strength was only 7kg though...
壊す気で来てください
Come at me with the intention of breaking me!
行きますよ！8倍！
Here I go! 8 times stronger!
もっと本気で来い！
Come at me with more effort!
あ〜〜っ！！う、腕がぁぁぁ！
Aaaah! My-my arm is...!
力の入れ方ってものを教えてやる！ / やめてください！
I'll show you how to apply power! / Please stop!
莉々華 大丈夫？動く？ / 大丈夫です
Ririka, are you okay? Can you move it? / I'm okay!
もうちょっとで壊すところでした
I was just about to break it.
本当にホロメンは力の弱い子が多いので僕がおかしいような雰囲気がよく漂いますが
Honestly, so many Hololive members are weak, so there's often an vibe that I'm the weird one...
そんなキャラとツッコミキャラ、大きなターニングポイントとなりました
That persona, along with the "straight man persona", became a major turning point.
当時マインクラフトのホロサーバー内にかなた城を建設していた僕なんですが
Back then, I was building Kanata Castle on the Hololive Minecraft server...
それを見たフレア先輩が「かなた学校建設予定地」と看板を書き、「学校じゃねーからこれ！」と思わず言ったと
Flare-senpai saw it and put up a sign saying "Kanata School Construction Site", so I blurted out, "This isn't a school!"
そしたらみこ先輩もきて「AO入学可能」と。学校いじりのボケが続いたので「学校じゃねーよ！」とツッコミ続けたと
Then Miko-senpai came and wrote "AO Admission Available". Since the school jokes kept coming, I kept retorting, "It's not a school!"
分かる〜！ そうだね
I get it! Yeah, totally.
そうなんですよ
That's right.
ボケ属性のね ホロメンが非常に多いんですよ
There are so many Hololive members with "boke" (funny/dofy) traits.
ということでね 僕はこうなります 次のページ
So, this is what happened to me. Next page!
クセつよだらけのホロライブ 「ツッコミ属性」に一筋の光！
In a Hololive full of quirky characters, a ray of light shines on the "tsukkomi" role!
そうなんです 僕はここからツッコミについて学び出します
Exactly. From here, I started learning how to be the "tsukkomi" (straight man).
真面目に学び出しましてね
I started studying it seriously.
ちゃんとツッコミできるようになったら 役割的にもいいのかなと思って
I thought if I could handle the tsukkomi role, it'd give me a solid place.
テレビを見て参考にしたツッコミ芸人の方がいらっしゃいます
There was a specific comedian I watched on TV to learn tsukkomi from.
その方がこちら 次のページ
And that person is... Next page!
くりぃむしちゅーの上田さん！
Cream Stew's Ueda-san!
あ〜 なるほど！ 確かに確かに！
Ah, I see! Definitely, definitely!
ツッコミだよね！
He's the ultimate tsukkomi!
『しゃべくり007』とかを見て 面白いなと思って
I watched "Shabekuri 007" and found it hilarious,
上田さんを参考に ツッコミを勉強しました
so I studied tsukkomi using Ueda-san as a reference.
例えツッコミが多くて
He uses a lot of metaphorical retorts,
すごく難しいんですけど こんな風になりたいと思い勉強しました
which is super difficult, but I studied wanting to be like that.
元々一方的に喋ってしまう オウム返しするみたいなことがあったけど
Originally, I tended to just talk endlessly or parrot things back,
ツッコミを意識してからは しっかり相手の言葉を聞いたり 待つこともできるようになりました
but once I focused on tsukkomi, I learned to listen to others and wait my turn.
すごーい！ 素晴らしい！ ありがとうございます！
Amazing! Wonderful! Thank you so much!
こうして僕はツッコミで自分のポジションを開拓していくこととなります
And so, I carved out my own niche using tsukkomi.
ここまでの教訓としましては... 次のページ！
The lesson up to this point... Next page!
自然とキャラはついてくる！ 焦って無理しても空回りするだけ！
"Character traits will follow naturally! Rushing and forcing it only leads to spinning your wheels!"
なるほどー！
I see!
無理してキャラ付けしなくても 勝手についていって自分も楽
You don't have to force a persona; it develops on its own and makes things easier.
配信の中で 自然と自分に合ったキャラがついてくる
During streams, a character that fits you naturally emerges.
焦らずホロメンと喋ったり 配信のいいやり方を見つける
So don't rush, talk with fellow members, and find a streaming style that works best for you.
キャラをどうしようとか 自分の理想もあるし 求められるものの違いとかあると思うんだけど
I know you worry about your persona, have your own ideals, and deal with expectations,
1番やりやすいのが 配信をたくさんするので絶対いい
but streaming a lot every day is honestly the best path.
今「キャラ無い」とか思っても いつか絶対ついてくるから 本当に大丈夫です
Even if you feel like you don't have a persona right now, one will definitely form eventually.
この配信マジで...
Seriously, this stream...
全ホロライブの新人に見せる会やった方がいい！ マジで！
...needs to be mandatory viewing for every new Hololive recruit! Seriously!
まず入ったらこの配信を見てもらう 「とりあえず見ろ」つって
As soon as they join, they should watch this stream. Just tell them, "Watch this first!"
配信にも慣れていった僕ですが
So, as I gradually got used to streaming,
もともとホロライブに入ってやりたかったことがありました 次のページ
there was something I originally really wanted to do when joining Hololive. Next page!
歌です！
Singing!
歌ね！ イメージある！ ありがとうございます！
Singing! That definitely fits you! Thank you!
子供の頃からアイドルに憧れ続けておりまして
I've always admired idols ever since I was a kid.
パワーポイントデビュー配信でも ライブでコール＆レスポンスするのが目標と言っていたりしました
Even during my PowerPoint debut stream, I said my goal was to do call-and-response at a live concert.
当時は明確な目標はなく いつかソロライブできたらなーって感じで
Back then, I didn't have a concrete plan, just a vague dream of doing a solo concert someday.
そんなすぐにもと思ってなかったです
I didn't think it would happen anytime soon.
歌が大好きな僕は 2020年の7月くらいから
Because I loved singing, starting around July 2020,
月曜日の夜に毎週歌枠をやってました
I started doing weekly singing streams on Monday nights.
いろんな方に歌聴いて欲しい 歌上手くなりたいと思ってやってて
I wanted many people to listen and wanted to improve my singing,
自分でもすごく楽しみにしていた歌枠だったんですけど
so these streams were something I personally looked forward to deeply.
そんな僕に異変が起きます 次のページ
But then, something strange happened to me. Next page.
耳の持病が悪化
My chronic ear condition worsened.
そうなんですよ
That's right.
え これどんな症状だったんでしたっけ？
Um, what kind of symptoms did you have?
元々デビュー前から 高い音が聞こえにくいとか
Even before my debut, I had trouble hearing high pitches,
低音が聞こえにくいとか色々あったんですけど
and low pitches were also hard to hear among other issues.
この頃はちょっと悪化しまして
Around this time, it worsened significantly,
片方の耳はほぼ聞こえてない
and I could barely hear out of one ear.
聞こえてないけど 常に耳鳴りがいつもしてたり
Though I couldn't hear well, I had constant tinnitus,
何かの特定の音が割れて聞こえるような状態になっておりまして
and certain specific frequencies sounded distorted and crackly to me.
耳が聞こえづらいと 歌にどんな影響が出してしまうのか？
What kind of impact does impaired hearing have on singing?
次のページ
Next page!
自分の歌声がわからない
"I can't tell what my own singing voice sounds like."
自分が歌ってる音程も ちょっとずれて聞こえる時があるし
Sometimes the pitch I was singing sounded off to me,
声の大きさがわからなくて 大きく出しちゃう 力んじゃうとか
and because I couldn't gauge my volume, I'd sing too loudly or strain myself.
うまく歌えなくて すごく難しい
I couldn't sing well, and it was extremely difficult.
となると あれだけ好きだった歌が嫌いになってくるんですよ
Because of that, the singing I loved so much started becoming something I hated.
歌わないと 喉の筋肉も終わっていき
If you don't sing, your vocal muscles deteriorate,
どんどん下手になって あーもう嫌だと
making you sing worse and worse until you just feel sick of it.
お医者さんからも「1回お休みした方がいいんじゃないか」と言われ
And my doctor advised, "It might be best if you take a break."
結果 次のページ
As a result... Next page.
毎週やっていた歌枠が終了
"Weekly singing streams ended."
悲しいよ...
That's so sad...
ちょっとここはね 悲しいところなんですけど すごく悲しかったですね
Yeah, this was a sad period. It was really heartbreaking for me.
歌にハンデがあるっていうのは しょうがないと思いつつ
While I knew I had to accept the handicap in singing,
なんでこういう自分なのかなって 落ち込んだ時期もありました
there were times I felt deeply depressed, wondering why I was born like this.
が！ しかしそんな時に支えになったのがこちら
BUT! What supported me during that dark time was this...
次のページ！
Next page!
「リスナーの温かい言葉と仲間のホロメン」です
"Warm words from listeners and fellow Hololive members."
あったかーい！ いやもう本当に助かりましたね
So heartwarming! They truly saved me.
みんなに支えてもらって 時間がかかっても頑張ろうと思えてきまして
With everyone's support, I felt inspired to keep trying, even if it took time.
上がっていきましたね モチベーション
My motivation started climbing back up.
よかった〜！ ありがとうございます！
So glad! Thank you so much!
一番大好きな音楽が嫌いになって 趣味が1個なくなったって思ってたんですけど
I used to think I had come to hate my favorite thing, music, losing one of my passions...
リスナーさんからは
"From the listeners,"
「それでも歌大好きだよ」って言ってもらえて
'they told me, "We still love your singing,"'
まだやっててもいいのかな とか
'making me think, "Maybe it\'s okay for me to keep going?"'
思えましたし
"That's how I felt,"
そういう風に 今 絶対聞き苦しいのに
"and even though it must be hard to listen to right now,"
聞いてくれるみんなのために 頑張りたいと思いましたね
"I felt I wanted to do my best for everyone who listens to me."
心から
"From the bottom of my heart."
やっぱりリスナーさんからのさ 温かい言葉ってさ 心に残るし 嬉しいよね
"Warm words from listeners really stay in your heart and make you happy, don't they?"
嬉しい！
"It really makes you happy!"
そうだよね みんなあるよね そういうことね
"Right? Everyone has experienced that kind of thing, right?"
めっちゃあります！
"Definitely!"
ちょっとやっぱ落ち込んだ時とかに エゴサして 「今日も可愛かったな」とか
'When I\'m feeling a bit down, I vanity search and see comments like "She was cute today too," or'
「いっぱい頑張ってるね」とか
'or "She\'s working so hard," and...'
そういう優しいコメント見るだけで 胸がいっぱいになって
"Just seeing those kind comments makes my heart swell,"
「また頑張ろう」って気持ちに マジでなれます
'and it really makes me feel like doing my best again!'
ありがとう！
"Thank you!"
素敵だね
"That's so wonderful."
ラミィも 自分の体調の悪化で 配信がしばらくできなかった時期があるんだけど
"Lamy also had a period where I couldn't stream for a while due to my health worsening,"
その間にリスナーさんがずっと 「ラミィちゃんいつまでも待ってるからね」って
'and during that time, the listeners kept saying, "Lamy-chan, we\'ll wait for you forever,"'
「体調よく治すように ちゃんと今休むんだよ」って
'"Rest properly right now so you can get fully better,"'
ずっと待っててくれて
"and they kept waiting for me continuously."
実際復帰した時もみんな温かく 「ラミィちゃん待ってたよ」「良かったね」って出迎えてくれて
'When I actually came back, everyone warmly welcomed me saying "Lamy-chan, we were waiting for you! So glad you\'re back!"'
リスナーさんあの時はありがとう 雪民さんいつも大好きだよ
"Listeners, thank you so much for that time! Yukimin, I always love you!"
エモい！
"So emotional!"
おかゆ先輩もありますか？
"Okayu-senpai, do you have any stories like that?"
おかゆ先輩は体調崩したこととかはないけど
"Okayu-senpai hasn't really collapsed from bad health or anything, but..."
やっぱりこうゲームやっててめっちゃ悲しいシーンが来て エンエン泣いちゃったりして鼻ずっぴずびになったりするんだけど
"when I'm playing games and a super sad scene comes along, I end up crying uncontrollably and getting all sniffling and snotty..."
「ゆっくりでいいよ」「ゆっくり鼻かんでいいよ」って
'"Take your time," "It\'s okay to take your time blowing your nose,"'
言ってくる優しさを感じますね いつも本当に
"They say things like that, so I really always feel their kindness."
鼻かもう / ありがとね / 優しいね
"Blow your nose! / Thank you. / They're so kind."
あとたくさんホロメンにも応援してもらって
"Also, I've received a lot of support from Holo-members too."
例えばフレア先輩から 「耳の病気とかハンデがあっても その上でも歌上手だからすごいよ！」って言ってもらったりして 勇気づけられたりとか
'For example, Flare-senpai told me, "Even with ear illness and handicaps, you\'re still a great singer, so you\'re amazing!" which really encouraged me.'
あとは同期の桐生ココというね 人がいたんですけれけれども ま今卒業してしまいましたが
"And then there was my Gen-mate Kiryu Coco... though she has graduated now."
当時一緒の家で同居していたので
"At the time, we were living in the same house together,"
僕が落ち込んでいる時 特に何か言いうわけでもなく
"so when I was feeling down, without saying anything special in particular,"
「あ、飯食う？」みたいな感じて
'she\'d just be like, "Ah, wanna eat?"'
一緒に味噌汁食べたりとか
"and we'd eat miso soup together..."
午前3時におやつ食べたりとか
"or eat snacks at 3:00 AM..."
そういうのができたのが 今思うとすごく助かりました
"Being able to do things like that was a huge help in hindsight."
そんな時に大事件が起きます
"Right at that time, a major event occurred."
次のページ
"Next page."
同期メンバーの「卒業」です
'The graduation of a Gen-mate.'
これはですね 4期生は元々 今4人なんですけど5人おりまして
"Well, 4th Gen originally... we are 4 now, but there were 5 of us,"
同期の天才のように面白かった桐生ココが 卒業することになりました
"and Kiryu Coco, who was as funny as a genius, decided to graduate."
何より同居して生活を共にしたのもあって いろんな話も聞いていたし 仲も一番よかったかなと思います
"Above all, living together and sharing life, I listened to various stories and we were probably the closest."
その時に活動の先に求めるものとか 生活の感じとかも色々似ていて 本当に気が合ったというか
"At the time, what we sought beyond our activities, our daily life rhythm, many things were similar, and we really clicked."
そんなココの卒業っていうのは 僕にとってもかなり大きい出来事でございました
"So Coco's graduation was quite a huge event for me as well."
莉々華は喋ったことないもんね
"Ririka, you've never spoken with her, right?"
そうですね 莉々華が入った時にはご卒業されてたんですけど
"That's right, by the time Ririka joined, she had already graduated,"
伝説のドラゴンのイメージがすごくあって 最強の人っていうイメージがあります
"but I strongly held the image of the legendary dragon, like she was the strongest person."
そうだよ 僕たちココちゃんとかかなたんの前から入ってるメンバーから見ても やっぱココちゃんはすごい伝説を残していった印象ありますよ
"That's right. Even looking from the perspective of members like us who joined before Coco-chan and Kanatan, Coco-chan really left behind a legendary legacy."
4期生がホロライブに入って ARKとかね 朝ココとかも 毎日胸がドキドキする時期だったし
"When Gen 4 joined Hololive, with ARK and AsaCoco, it was a time when your heart raced every day,"
毎日の朝のライブ配信とか 他のホロメンの情報まとめてニュースでやるっていうのがすごく斬新で 天才だったなって
"and doing daily morning live streams summarizing news of other Holomembers was super innovative, she was a genius."
本当そうですよね 準備とかも大変な中 そういうこともやって 箱のためになったらいいとすごく考える人でしたね
"That's so true. Even with prep work being tough, she did all that, always thinking deeply about how to benefit the agency."
そんな風に仲がよかったからこそ 卒業が完全に決まった時は 悲しい気持ちはもちろんありました
"Because we were so close like that, when her graduation was fully finalized, I naturally felt very sad."
ココの卒業を聞いた時 最後にやりたかったことがありました それがこちら 次のページ
"When I heard about Coco's graduation, there was one thing I wanted to do at the end. That is this! Next page!"
4期生としてのオリジナル楽曲
"An original song as Gen 4."
やっぱり折角なら 5人のオリジナル曲欲しいよなって思ったんですよね
"I thought, since we have the chance, I really want an original song with all 5 of us."
そこで運営さんに「4期生の曲作りたい」と言うと こう言われます 次のページ
'So when I told staff, "I want to make a Gen 4 song," this is what they told me. Next page!'
「間に合いません」 / 時間がね...
'"We won\'t make it in time." / Time-wise...'
曲の制作には時間かかりますし 卒業が決まった時には もう「今からの楽曲制作は間に合わない」と はっきり言われました
'Song production takes time, and by the time graduation was decided, they clearly told me, "Starting song production now won\'t make it in time."'
これを言われた僕はこう思います 次のページ
"Having been told this, I thought like this. Next page!"
「だったらを自分で作っちゃおう」 / よくそうなった！
'"Then I\'ll just make it myself!" / How did you reach that decision? Amazing!'
発注すると間に合わないなら 自分で作れば間に合うだろう
If ordering it won't be in time, I can just make it myself, I thought...
と思って 初めての作詞作曲をします
So I decided to try writing lyrics and composing for the first time.
で こうしてできた楽曲が次のページ
And the song created like this is on the next page.
4期生5人で歌う 最初で最後のオリジナル楽曲 『キセキ結び』
The first and last original song sung by all five 4th gen members, "Kiseki Musubi".
はい こちらね 当時の僕が思いを込めて
Yes. This song was made with all my feelings at the time,
いろんな方に協力していただいて 発表することができました
and with everyone's help, we were able to release it.
映像があるのでご覧ください
We have a video, so please take a look.
約束しよう 僕が出会えたキセキ
Let's make a promise, the miracle that brought us together...
忘れないように
So that we'll never forget it.
キセキ結び - ホロライブ4期生
"Kiseki Musubi" - Hololive 4th Gen
夢抱いて集う 青春アニメみたいな
Gathering with dreams, like a youth anime...
ハッピーなエンドになる 彼方へ跳ぶよ
Aiming for a happy ending, jumping into the distance!
寝ぼけ目あくびして 今日は何をしようか
Yawning with sleepy eyes, what shall we do today?
永久に続く海を駆け抜ける
Running across the endless sea...
今はため息よりも勇気を
Right now, courage over sighs...
諦めるなんてないの
There's no such thing as giving up!
ここで歌う 僕の
Singing right here, my...
声は聞こえてますか？
Can you hear my voice?
学校の友達じゃ きっとない出会いだった
We definitely wouldn't have met as school friends.
画面の先の遥か遠くまで
To far beyond the other side of the screen...
ささくれた言葉も 誰かの笑顔になる
Even harsh words turn into someone's smile.
それぞれの色で 星結ぶキセキ
Connecting stars in our own colors, a miracle...
キラキラ輝くステージに 連れてくよ
We'll take you to the sparkling stage!
はい ありがとう御座います！ めっちゃよかった〜
Thank you so much! That was so good~!
ありがとうございました
Thank you very much.
いや メロディも歌詞も良くて
Honestly, both the melody and lyrics are so great...
この曲を作っていた当時 おかゆ先輩とめっちゃ遊んでて
Back when I was making this song, I hung out with Okayu-senpai so much...
めっちゃ遊んでた 毎日会ってたよね
We hung out a lot! We literally met up every day.
その時かなたんが「僕今作詞 頑張ってて」って
Back then, Kanatan told me, "I'm working hard on writing lyrics right now."
完成した曲がこんないい曲だから
And the finished song turned out to be so amazing!
すっごい褒めてくれて
She praised me so much...
歌詞の中にみんなの名前入ってるって エモエモすぎんか？
The fact that everyone's name is in the lyrics, isn't that so emotional?
天才でしょ これ
She's a genius, right?
いろんな人に助けていただいて
No no, I was really helped by so many people...
こうしてここを送り出すことになったんですけれど
And so, it led to seeing Coco off like this...
悲しんだりとか 寂しがってるだけではいけない
I thought that we shouldn't just be sad or lonely.
この頃の人生グラフはこうなっております
My life graph around this time looked like this. Next page.
上がってきたー！
It went back up!
周りと比較するより 過去の自分と比較するっていうのが1番いい
We often talked about how comparing yourself to your past self is better than comparing yourself to others...
そういうことを続けて 自分を磨いていこうと
I talked with Coco about that a lot, and decided to keep working on myself.
改めて歌に力を入れていくんですが
From then on, I refocused my efforts on singing...
ソロライブをやるにはどうすればいいか？っていうのを考えた時に
When I thought about how to hold a solo live...
天音かなた＝歌
I thought of establishing the image of "Amane Kanata = Singing" first.
そのために意識していたことがあります
For that purpose, there's something I kept in mind. That's on the next page.
他のメンバーのライブに多数ゲスト出演
Guest starring in lots of other members' live concerts.
記念ライブにホロメンをゲストで呼ぶのが当たり前の時代
Back then, inviting Holo members as guests for anniversary lives was the norm...
頂いたオファーも本当にありがたい機会
So any offers I received were truly grateful opportunities...
祝う気持ちが1番ですけど 自分がいっぱい歌を歌いたい もっと成長したいという思い
While celebrating them was top priority, wanting to sing more and grow motivated me...
オファーを片っ端から引き受けていきました さらにこんなことをしてみます
To accept every single offer. Furthermore, I tried doing this. Next page.
2周年記念LIVEでゲストなしのソロライブ
A solo live with no guests for my 2nd anniversary live.
天音かなた2周年LIVE「リベンジ」
Yes, in my 2nd anniversary live "Revenge"...
ゲストがいるのが当たり前の時代 ソロライブをする人がいなくなっていた
it had become the norm to have guests, and almost nobody was doing solo lives...
ゲストを呼ばず1時間で15曲 挑戦的にやってみたりもしました
So I took on the challenge of doing a 1-hour live with 15 songs and no guests.
この頃から自分の歌についても真剣に向き合うようになっていく
So around this time, I started taking my own singing very seriously...
一から発声や歌い方を見直すことになります
I decided to re-evaluate my vocalization and singing style from scratch.
やったことがこちら 次のページ
And here's what I did. Next page.
自分の歌い方の「癖」の選別 人気曲のボーカルだけを抽出して分析 昔の曲の研究
Sorting out the "habits" of my singing style, extracting and analyzing vocals of popular songs, and studying old songs.
歌い方の癖の選別ってなに？
What is "sorting out habits of singing style"...?
この癖なんですけど
Speaking of these singing habits...
強い癖があった方が個性があっていいとか、癖がない方が聞きやすいよとかあったんですけど
...there were opinions that strong habits give character, or having no habits makes it easier to listen to.
まずは自分はやっぱり癖はどちらかというと強いから、じゃあどこを残そうかと考えた時に
Since my habits were on the stronger side, when I thought about which parts to keep...
まずは癖をゼロにしようと思いまして
...I decided to reset my vocal habits to zero first.
ちょうど「歌ってみた」で「炉心融解」とかボーカロイドの曲歌ったんですけど、その時も癖ゼロでボカロみたいに歌うことを意識したりしました。
When I did cover songs like Vocaloid's 'Roshin Yuukai', I focused on singing like a Vocaloid with zero habit.
いい癖は残して、ま、ちょっと聞きにくいなっていう癖はなるべくなくすっていうことで、ちょっとブラッシュアップをしていこうと思ってましたね。
I wanted to polish my singing by keeping the good habits and eliminating the hard-to-listen ones.
いや、でも思った。一時系列のときから、かなたんの歌い方変わったなって思った。
I actually noticed it too. At one point, I thought Kanatan's singing style changed.
そうなんですよ。おかゆ先輩ともね、いっぱい「歌ってみた」ね、歌わせていただいたりしてるんですけど、初期の頃「歌ってみた」やってる時はまだ選別前で…
Exactly. I've covered many songs with Okayu-senpai, but back during my early covers, it was before I filtered my habits...
ちょっとブスの時。
...when my voice was a bit rough.
ちょいブスの時ね！ / そんなことない！
When your voice was a bit rough, right? / Not at all!
みたいな感じ、ただこれは結構辛い作業で、これは実は1年かかりまして、選別しましたね。
Something like that. But this was quite a tough process, and it actually took me a whole year to sort out.
あと、人気の曲、ま、例えば、YOASOBIさんとかの流行りのアーティスト、やっぱ流行りの歌い方っていうものがあるなっていうのを感じて
Also, analyzing popular songs—for example, trending artists like YOASOBI—I felt there was a trending style of singing.
そういう方々のボーカルを聞いて「こういう癖は入れるけど、ここには入れない」んだとか、そういうの研…研究というか分析しましたね。
Listening to their vocals, I analyzed things like, "They add this nuance here, but not there."
勉強熱心や。 / 流行りがありつつも、そこに寄せるか寄せまいかっていうのはすごく考えましたね。
You're so dedicated. / While trends exist, I really thought hard about whether to conform to them or not.
あとは昔の歌も研究して、曲にも流行りの周期があって、ロックっぽいのが流行ったり、バラードが流行ったり、今ちょっとエモ系だったり、
I also researched older songs. Music has trend cycles—rock, ballads, or current emo style—
昔流行った曲とかその時に流行ってる歌い方とかもかなり研究を…
...so I heavily studied past hit songs and singing styles from those eras too.
なんかつっこみも色々勉強されてたみたいな話もあったし、今回もいろいろ研究して、本当に努力家というか… / ありがとう、120点のコメント！
You mentioned studying comedy retorts before, and now researching music like this... you're a hard worker. / Thank you for that 120-point comment!
まあ、とにかくこれほどしないと、自分の耳の癖もありますし、ちょっと聞きづらくなってる歌っていうのが、なかなか変えられないなということで1からやろうと思って
Anyway, without going this far, personal biases and hard-to-listen habits are tough to fix, so I decided to start from scratch.
これをやった結果、昔3時間かかっていたレコーディングが、今は20分くらいで終わるようになりました！
As a result, recording that used to take 3 hours in the past now takes about 20 minutes!
ありがとうございます。これもレコーディングをやる時に「この癖を入れたいな」って何回も試すとかやってたんですけど、それがパッとできるようになって、納得できる歌い方ができるようになったっていう感じでしたね。
Thank you. Before, I used to try a habit repeatedly during recording, but now I can do it instantly and sing in a way I'm satisfied with.
みなさんはレコーディングにこだわりってありますか？
Does everyone have any specific preferences or struggles when recording?
こだわりというか…今現在、生え…まさに自分の癖で悩んでて…
Rather than a preference... right now, I'm actually struggling with my own vocal habits.
歌って今までやってこなかったんだけど、ホロライブに入って歌を歌う機会がすごく増えて、初めて自分の癖みたいなのが出てきちゃってるの。
I hadn't sung much before, but joining Hololive gave me so many opportunities to sing, and for the first time, my habits are surfacing.
それを残した方がいいのか、省いてもっとまっさらな歌い方にしたらいいのか、すごい今リアルタイムで悩んでて…
I'm genuinely struggling right now over whether I should keep them or smooth them out into a completely plain singing style...
この件、かなたんに相談します！
...so I'm going to consult Kanatan about this!
待ってます！
I'll be waiting!
ふたりは？ / リリカは…なんか感情が死んでるのか分かんないんですけど… / どういうこと？！
What about you two? / For me, I don't know if my emotions are dead or what... / What do you mean?!
歌う時に感情を乗せるのがあんまり得意じゃなくて、歌詞の意味とかが頭を通り抜けちゃうんですよ。
I'm not very good at putting emotion into singing; the meaning of the lyrics just passes right through my head.
なるべく情景を思い描きながら歌うように頑張ってるんで、まずは感情を取り戻すところから… / 化け物かもしれない / そんなことないですよ！
So I try my best to picture the scene while singing. I'm starting by recovering my emotions... / Maybe a monster / Not at all!
おかゆ先輩感情入れて歌うの逆に得意な気がしますけど。
Okayu-senpai, on the other hand, seems really good at singing with emotion.
僕とかかなたんって、ミックスの勉強もしてたことあったじゃん？だからミックスするとどうしても表情感って消えやすい…
Kanatan and I used to study audio mixing, right? When you mix, expressiveness easily gets lost...
ピッチの補正でね。 / 補正で消えるんだよ！ / ピッチを取るか表現を取るか考えること多いかもね。
...due to pitch correction. / Pitch correction erases it! / So we often have to choose between exact pitch and expression.
そうなんですよね。音程を気にするとやっぱり表情が落ちていくのは絶対あるから、「この1行めっちゃいいからここだけ入れよう」とか決めるとやりやすいかも。
Exactly. Focusing on pitch definitely reduces expression, so deciding "This line is great, let's keep the emotion just here" makes it easier.
めっちゃ勉強になる！タメになる～！
That's so educational! So helpful~!
と言いつつ、僕もまだまだでございますが、こういった地道な活動の結果、2022年の年末に行われた3周年記念ライブ「別世界」ではこうなります！次のページ！
Though I still have a long way to go, here is the result of these steady efforts from my 3rd Anniversary Live "Another World" in late 2022! Next page!
「21秒のロングトーン 歌が大反響！」 / すごいんだから！ありがとう！
"21-second long tone song receives massive acclaim!" / That's amazing! Thank you!
このライブのね
It looks like there's a video of the long-tone part of that live concert,
ロングトーン部分の映像があるみたいなのでご覧ください
so please take a look!
よろしければご覧ください どうぞ！
If you'd like, please check it out. Here you go!
ショートとかでもめっちゃ流れてくるからね
That clip pops up on Shorts all the time, right?
そうそう！
Yeah, it really does!
僕じゃない人がショートたくさん切り抜いてるからね
People other than me keep clipping it for Shorts because it's so amazing!
「驚異の」みたいな...
Titled things like "Mind-boggling vocal range"...
何回も見たいよここ
I want to rewatch this part over and over!
やばい もう息したい
Oh man, I want to take a breath already!
息したい 息したい
I wanna breathe! I wanna breathe!
喉苦しい 喉苦しい
My throat hurts! My throat hurts!
こっから上がんのがすごいよね！
It's amazing how it goes even higher from here!
本当に！ 上がる！？ってなるよね
Seriously! You're like, "It goes even higher?!"
どうやって...？
How does she even do that...?
まじでやばい
Seriously insane!
最後のビブラートね
And that final vibrato!
まだ残ってるのかっつって
You're left thinking, "She still had breath left?!"
ありがとうございます
Thank you so much!
すごい技術だよ これ
That is such incredible vocal technique!
とんでもなく練習したんですけども
I practiced insanely hard for that...
これは実は元をたどると ちょっと逃げのロングトーンで
Actually, if you trace it back to the origin, it was kind of a "cop-out" long tone...
ええ！？ なぜ逃げだったかというと
Eh!? What do you mean cop-out?!
どこに逃げたの？
Where did you run away to?!
この「unravel」という楽曲 ここでデスボイスが本家だと
In this song "unravel", the original uses death voice screaming here...
ヴヅーーーって ウォー！って出るの
It goes "VRRRGH!" and "WAAAA!"
それができないんで ロングトーンにした
I couldn't do that scream, so I made it a long tone instead!
逃げではない 逃げてない 挑戦だよ！
No way! That's not a cop-out, that's a whole challenge!
デスボイスから逃げてきて ロングトーンとなったんですが
So I ran away from death voice and turned it into a long tone, but...
やりたいことをかなり詰め込んだライブが成功して
The live concert where I packed in everything I wanted to do was a success...
100万人記念の新衣装も見せるタイミングだったり
And it was right around the timing to show my 1 Million subscriber outfit...
「unravel」でロングトーンしたことを 思った以上に色んな方に見ていただいて
Far more people than I expected saw that long-tone part in "unravel"...
「今までで1番ライブよかった！」という反響をいただいたり
I received feedback like "That was your best live concert ever!"...
「歌上手くなったね」って言ってもらえるのがすごく嬉しくて まだ頑張っていこうと思いました
Hearing people say "Your singing got so good" made me so happy that I wanted to keep trying my best.
この時の反響がなければ 今自分は必死に歌頑張るということはなかったかなと思います
Without the reaction from that performance, I don't think I'd be pushing myself this hard with singing today.
そのあとね 去年3月に天音かなたファーストアルバム「Unknown DIVA」を発表することもできまして
And after that, in March last year, I was able to release my 1st album CD "Unknown DIVA"...
見事完売できまして
And it completely sold out!
素晴らしい！ すご〜い！
Wonderful! Amazing!
運営さんも頑張ったと認めてくれたって感じましたし
I felt like management acknowledged how hard I had worked,
へい民のみんなが嬉しそうにしてくれたり 好きな曲を発見してくれたりしてすごく嬉しかった
and above all, seeing all the Heimins listen happily and discover songs they liked made me so glad.
そしてなんと！
And guess what!
今年7月23日にはセカンドアルバム「Trigger」を発売します！
On July 23rd this year, I will be releasing my 2nd album "Trigger"!
さらにさらに 8月13日は待望のソロライブを開催させていただくことになりました！
And what's more! On August 13th, I will be holding my long-awaited solo live concert!
おめでと〜！ ありがとうございます
Congratulations~! Thank you so much!
このアルバムの「Trigger」は ジャケットとかアナザージャケットを自分で発注からやって クオリティにこだわっていたり
For this album "Trigger", I handled everything from ordering the jacket and alt jacket art myself, focusing heavily on quality...
楽曲なんですけど「十万億土」という楽曲を作詞作曲してみました
And for the tracks, I actually wrote and composed a song called "Jumankuokudo"!
ラップを入れてみたり挑戦してみたので 是非チェックして欲しいです
I challenged myself by adding rap parts to it, so I really hope you check it out!
めっちゃ楽しみ〜！
I'm looking forward to it so much~!
他にも「世界で一番のアイドル」という楽曲の作詞もしまして
I also wrote the lyrics for a song called "Sekai de Ichiban no Idol"...
「十万億土」とは全く違く 韻などは踏んでおりません
Unlike "Jumankuokudo", this one is just honest feelings—no rhyming scheme or anything!
素直な気持ちを文字にしたので 応援してくれるへい民に届いたらいいなと思っております
I just put my genuine feelings into words, so I hope it reaches the Heimins supporting me.
絶対届くよ！
It will definitely reach them!
全体的に歌がパワーアップしていると思いますので ソロライブを楽しみに探していてほしいと思います！
Overall, my singing has powered up, so I hope you look forward to the solo concert!
現在のhololive人生グラフはこうなります 次のページ！
Here is my current Hololive life graph! Next page!
おお〜上がってる！ 上昇してる〜！
Ooh~ It's going up! It's rising~!
現在右肩上がりで順調にいかさせていただいております
Right now, it's steadily trending upwards!
それもこれも ここに集まってくれた3人 本当に心から感謝している
All of this is thanks to the three of you here, I'm truly grateful from the bottom of my heart...
来てもらってお忙しい中
Thank you so much for coming despite your busy schedules...
カニが待っているからな！ カニ食べたい〜！
Crab is waiting for us! I wanna eat crab~!
奢りたいと思います
I'll treat you all to crab!
最後に僕のデビュー配信を振り返らせていただきますが デビュー配信でこんなことを言っていました こちら
Lastly, let's look back at my debut stream. Here's what I said back then!
僕が初配信でこうやっていっぱい話した 突拍子もない夢を
If I can someday fulfill these wild dreams I talked so much about during my debut stream...
いつか叶えることができたら
if I'm able to make them come true one day,
それはまず リスナーさん へい民の皆のおかげだから
that will be first and foremost thanks to all the listeners and Heimins...
こうして活動が始まったけど 最初から最後まで頑張って 自分も皆も今より幸せになるように
My activities have started like this, but I want to try my best from start to finish so both I and everyone else become happier than we are now...
それが天音かなたがVTuberとして活動する理由です
That is the reason Amane Kanata acts as a VTuber.
すごいよ初配信で！ しっかりしてる〜！
That's amazing for a debut stream! She was already so well-grounded~!
当時は突拍子もない夢だと思ってましたけど いろんな夢が叶うところまでこられた
Back then I thought they were crazy impossible dreams, but I've made it to the point where so many of them are coming true.
ということで いろんなしくじりや事件があって 紆余曲折しましたが
So, while there were various blunders and incidents, and many twists and turns...
今こうして天音かなたという僕 出来上がりました！ ありがとうございます！
...now, here I am, fully formed as Amane Kanata! Thank you so much!
皆さん、今日の授業いかがだったでしょうか？
Everyone, how was today's lesson?
めっちゃ良かったよ！ 超勉強になった！
It was really great! I learned so much!
かなたんが努力の人っていうのが この時間でものすごい分かったと思う
I think this lesson really showed us how hard-working Kanatan is.
本当だよね！ 本当ありがとう！
That's so true! Thank you so much!
いろんな苦労もあっただろうに それを感じさせず...
You must have gone through so many hardships, but you never let it show...
いやいやいや... 本当にね 僕正直 この授業 ホロメン全員分見たいぐらいあります！
No, no, no... Honestly, I'd love to see a lesson like this for every single Holo-member!
みんなの人生を教えてくれ！
"Tell me about all your lives!" I'd say.
ということでね 歌の話もしーの ちょっと実はね はっきり言ってこれはね 収録なんです！
So, after talking about singing... to be totally honest with you all, this is actually pre-recorded!
はっきり言って 収録だから 僕たち今 過去から来ています！
Exactly! Because it's pre-recorded, we're currently speaking to you from the past!
未来の僕 今ここから 生で続きの配信してくるので！
So, the future me will now take over and continue the stream live from here!
じゃあ 未来に行ってくる！
Well then, I'm heading off to the future!
あれ？ 置いていかれる感じ？ 僕たちはこの後どうしたら？
Wait! Are we being left behind? What are we supposed to do after this?
カニ行こうな！！
Let's go get crab!!
いえ〜い！！ カニ〜〜〜！
Yay!! Crab~~~!
行ってくる〜！ 未来に！
Off I go~! To the future!
手詰まりな現状の行き場が とめどなかった感情と交差する
The dead-end reality crosses paths with my unstoppable emotions.
どうしたってもう変えられない それはきっと個人の過護じゃない
Nothing can be changed anymore. Surely it's not just an individual's flaw.
セーブの手が効くのは 限られた範囲の話で
Relief works only within a limited range,
そこから外れちゃっちゃあ不干渉 どうせ何を言ったって勝機がないんだって
Outside of which lies indifference—say what you will, there's no chance of winning.
自分の塔は高すぎて びくともしない机上の仮説
My tower is too high—a mere theoretical hypothesis that won't budge.
それならこれからの方法も 知らないからね
In that case, I don't know what methods to take from now on anyway.
変わらない後悔があったって 今できることなんて何もないんだ
Even if there's unchanging regret, there's nothing that can be done right now.
どこいこうと苦戦はさけられない 決まり切った事実 擦り寄りそうもない
Wherever I go, a hard struggle is unavoidable; a fixed reality that won't compromise.
停滞していても最前提 嫌気がさすんだ
Even in stagnation, it's the premise—I'm getting disgusted by it.
今のままじゃあ滑落するだろう そして生真面目に心が軽くなってしまう
As things stand, I'll probably fall; and seriously, my heart ends up feeling lighter.
認めきれない言葉の連鎖で きっと僕らは無力であって
Through a chain of unacknowledgeable words, surely we are powerless,
思慮の行方が定まらないなら いっそ何もわからないままで
And if the destination of our thoughts remains unclear, I'd rather stay knowing nothing at all.
収まりきれない常識の尺度は 絶対的に正しくないが
The scale of common sense that can't fit in is by no means absolutely correct,
僕の手におえない君の理はどうやったって救い様がない
But your logic beyond my control is beyond salvation no matter what.
君らが慈愛を請うたって 正直役目の管轄外
Even if you beg for mercy, honestly it's outside my jurisdiction.
結局未来の想定も セルフとなってます
In the end, assumptions of the future are up to self-service as well.
しょうもない救済を待っていても 神様も救いはやってこないし
Even if you wait for some silly salvation, God's help won't come either,
時間が超過しすぎるだけ 止め処ない思考 事象を知らず
And time will just pass by too much—unending thoughts, ignorant of facts.
変わらない後悔があったって 今できることなんて何もないんだ
Even if there's unchanging regret, there's nothing that can be done right now.
どこいこうと苦戦はさけられない 決まり切った事実 擦り寄りそうもない
Wherever I go, a hard struggle is unavoidable; a fixed reality that won't compromise.
十人十色関係なく 自分のことで精一杯なんだ
Regardless of individual traits, everyone's full with their own affairs.
空を飛ぶための羽も買い 自分の足で歩くしかないのだろう
Buying wings to fly through the sky, there's no choice but to walk on our own feet.
みんな！ 見ましたか？ みんなー！
Everyone! Did you watch it? Everyone~!
帰ってきたよ！ ちょっと... この教室で...
I'm back! Man... back in this classroom...
ちょっと一回生きて... 誰もいない！
Wait a second, let me catch my breath... Nobody's here!
おい！ 勝手に帰ったー！
Hey! They went home on their own!
いやー、ありがとうございました！
Well, thank you so much!
ということで、すごい楽しかったよね！
So, that was really fun, wasn't it!
パチパチありがとう！ 今歌った曲なんですが、新曲になります！
Thank you for the applause! The song I just sang is actually a new song!
こちら！ 7月23日水曜日に発売予定の僕の2ndアルバム『Trigger』から、サツキさんに制作いただいた『セルフサービス』を初披露させていただきました！
Here it is! I just premiered "Self Service," produced by Satsuki, from my 2nd album "Trigger," set to release on Wednesday, July 23rd!
本日この後21時からMVを公開！ そして24時から各配信サービスにて音源リリース予定です！
Today, the music video will be released at 21:00! And the audio track will be released on streaming services at 24:00!
そして！ アルバム追加情報として『Trigger』に収録されている全9曲もの情報を...
And! As additional album info, here is the track list for all 9 songs included in "Trigger"...
初公開！
First reveal!
今回も超豪華作家陣の皆様に素敵な全9曲作っていただきました！
Once again, an incredible lineup of creators made 9 amazing songs for us!
アルバムはアクスタ3種セットや限定ホロカードが付いている超豪華な完全生産限定盤、
The album comes in a super deluxe limited edition with a set of 3 acrylic stands and exclusive holocards,
そしてA・Bの2形態ご用意している通常盤の計3種が
and two standard versions, Type A and B, making three types in total,
大大大好評予約受付中ですので、ぜひぜひ手に入れてくださいね！
which are now available for pre-order to overwhelmingly great response, so please get yours!
そして、YouTubeご覧の皆様は配信画面の下にね
And for those watching on YouTube, below the stream frame,
タグ付けされてる商品の購入ボタンからご予約できますのでチェックしてください！絶対頑張って設定したから多分いるはず...
you can pre-order from the tagged product buttons, so please check them out! I worked super hard to set it up, so they should be there...
そして！
And now...
皆様お待たせ！ソロライブの追加の告知でございます！
The moment you've all been waiting for! An additional announcement regarding my solo live!
まずは...おお、ありがとね！まずはこちらの動画を、どうぞ！
First up... Oh, thank you! First, please check out this video!
狙いを定めたその先は、あなたの心――
Target locked—aimed right at your heart...
楽曲一発一発に
Into every single song,
“僕の感情”を込めて
"my emotions" are poured
全力で撃ち抜いていく
Shooting straight through with all my strength.
一人ひとりの感情に、確かな共鳴が広がっていく
A clear resonance [trigger] spreads through each and every emotion.
かっこいいー！
So cool!
ということで、今回のライブタイトルは「天音かなた 1st Solo Live "LOCK ON"」です！
So, the title of this live concert is "Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live 'LOCK ON'"!
2ndアルバム『Trigger』と繋がりも考えて、ライブでみんなをね、ガンガン撃ち抜いていくイメージでございます。
Connecting to my 2nd album 'Trigger', the image is shooting right through all of you at the live show!
キービジュアルは現実世界に天界の門が降臨した、異世界感のある雰囲気になってます。
The key visual has an otherworldly vibe, with the gates of the heavenly realm descending upon the real world.
どうですか？このクールでかっこいい僕を見てライブへの期待感爆上がり...
How is it? Seeing this cool and awesome me, your expectations for the live show must be skyrocketing...
有明アリーナも見ね、みんなお待たせしました！会場は有明アリーナで開催いたします！
Thank you all for waiting for Ariake Arena too! The venue will be Ariake Arena!
本当にね、たくさんの偉大な先輩たちもこちらでライブをやってきているので、頑張ろうと思います！
So many great seniors have held concerts here, so I'll do my absolute best!
今回のソロライブのハッシュタグはですね、#撃ち抜けかなたそ です！どんどんみんなポストして一緒にライブを盛り上げてくれー！
The hashtag for this solo live is #撃ち抜けかなたそ [#ShootThroughKanataso]! Everyone, keep posting and let me know you're excited!
そして！
And next!
ジャジャン！チケット情報はこちら！
Ta-da! Here is the ticket information!
S席、A席、B席の3種類をご用意いたしました。
We have three types of seats available: S, A, and B.
1次先行は、この後21時から申し込み開始となります！
First round lottery applications start tonight at 21:00!
これね、抽選なんでみんな慌てずに、大丈夫ですからね。
This is a lottery, so no need to rush, you'll be fine.
今回はチケット販売サイトのZAIKOで海外のへい民向けにも現地チケットを販売します！
This time, venue tickets for overseas Hey-mins will also be sold via ZAIKO!
世界中のね、へい民に会えるの楽しみにしてるからね、みんな！
I'm really looking forward to meeting Hey-mins from all over the world!
「会場にはおら行けないよ」って人も全然大丈夫！
For those saying "I can't go to the venue," don't worry at all!
配信チケットはSPWNとZAIKOで販売します。
Streaming tickets will be sold on SPWN and ZAIKO.
こちらも21時から販売開始なので、配信でね、ぜひ僕の勇姿を見に来てください！
Sales start at 21:00 as well, so please watch my grand performance on stream!
各学...じゃ、間違えたわ。各座席のエリアマップはこちら！
Each schoo... wait, I made a mistake. Here is the seat area map!
S席は1階と3階前方、A席は1階後方と2階、B席は3階後方と4階に分かれています。
S seats are 1F and front of 3F; A seats are rear of 1F and 2F; B seats are rear of 3F and 4F.
お前ら、いっぱいね、いっぱい来てね、散らばってくれ！
Everyone, come in big numbers and spread out all over!
そして、みんなお待ちかねのグッズ情報もあります！
And here's the merch info you've all been waiting for!
グッズもね、この後21時より販売開始してるので、まずはライブに欠かせない応援セットをご紹介！
Merch sales also start tonight at 21:00, so first let me introduce the essential Concert Support Set!
ジャジャン！
Ta-da!
きちゃー！
Here it is!
うぱおライトは見の通り、うぱおがモチーフになりました！お前らもずっと欲しいって言ってたもんね！ライブ会場をうぱおで埋め尽くしましょう！
As you can see, the Upao Light is themed after Upao! You guys kept saying you wanted one! Let's fill the venue with Upao!
Tシャツは今回のライブタイトルにある「LOCK ON」にちなんで、胸に照準マークをモチーフにプリントしてみました！
For the T-shirt, inspired by the live title "LOCK ON", I printed a target sight motif on the chest!
みんなのね、あの心臓を僕が思いっきり撃ち抜いてあげますので、ぜひ天界に遊びに来てください！ライブにもぜひ来てください！
I'll shoot straight through all your hearts with everything I've got, so please come visit heaven! Come to the live show!
フェイスタオルはロゴを大きくあしらったデザインになっていて、これもね、弾丸で撃ち抜かれたイメージでかっこいいので、そうですね、みんなTシャツと一緒に身につけてくれたら嬉しいなと思います！
The face towel features a bold logo design that looks awesome like it was shot through by bullets, so I'd love it if you wore it with the T-shirt!
セット特典のラバーバンドはクリア素材で涼しげなデザイン！ロゴが入った特別仕様なのでみんなぜひゲットしてね！内側に「COVER」って書いてありました！
The bonus rubber band in the set has a cool, clear design! It's a special edition with the logo, so make sure to get it! It says "COVER" on the inside!
それぞれのグッズは単品でも販売します！他の先行グッズはこちら！
Each item is also available individually! Here are the other pre-sale items!
ジャジャン！
Ta-da!
リングライトと法被も先行発送対象となります！法被欲しかったでしょー？
The Ring Light and Happi Coat are also eligible for early shipping! You wanted the Happi, right?
リングライトにもね、ここ撃ち抜いてってアピールできるように照準アイコン入れてみました！へい民のみんな、僕がね、どんどんお前らを撃ち抜いていくので、ぜひライブで光らせてください！
I put a target icon on the Ring Light too so you can signal "shoot here"! Hey-mins, I'll keep shooting you all down, so shine it at the live!
法被は背面にキービジュアルのかなたそを大きくあしらいました！キービジュアルの雰囲気に合わせて、ちょっと...
The Happi features the key visual Kanataso printed large on the back! Matching the vibe of the key visual, it's slightly...
ね、サイバーチックなデザインにもしてもらいましたが、ソーラン節もちょっと浮かぶよね。
I had them make it a cyber-chic design, but it also brings Soran Bushi to mind, right?
へみんのみな、お前らは当然フル装備で応援してくり... かなー！
Everyone in Hemin, you guys of course will support me in full gear... right?!
リングライト Happi はね、応援セットには実は含まれませんので、この辺ね、あの、注意してくださいね。
Ring lights and Happi aren't actually included in the support set, so please be careful about that.
そして、受注販売グッズは、こちら！じゃじゃーん！
And the order-made merchandise is right here! Ta-da!
これ、トートバッグがすごい！
This tote bag is amazing!
よかった、サンプル見てもらったんですけど、トートバッグはね、痛バッグとしても使えるように、缶バッジ飾れる透明のポケットがついてて、
I'm glad, I checked out the sample, and the tote bag has a transparent pocket to display button badges so it can be used as an ita-bag,
キャリーケースのハンドルに通せるように通し穴もあるので、旅行の時も片手で持ち運べると。すごいですね、これ。
and it also has a loop so you can slide it onto a suitcase handle, letting you carry it with one hand when traveling. This is awesome.
モチーフキーホルダーは、キービジュアルの僕の首元にあるドッグタグというものをイメージしました。
The motif keychain is inspired by the dog tag around my neck in the key visual.
かっこいいデザインなので、バッグやポーチにつけてみてください。
It's a cool design, so please try attaching it to your bag or pouch.
アクリルスタンドも、これもね、さっき見たらすごかった！
The acrylic stand, too! I looked at it earlier and it was incredible!
背景の展開トラスとかなたーそがね、別パーツになっているんで、立体的に飾られてます。すんごい立体感あった！もう4Dでしたね！
The background expansion truss and Kanata-so are separate parts, so it's displayed 3D style. The 3D feel was amazing! It was like 4D!
そしてそして最後にご注意情報です。
And lastly, an important notice.
グッズの販売期間は、このあと21時から、6月23日18時までです。
The sales period for the merch is from 21:00 today until June 23, 18:00.
んで、みんな、ややこしいからね、あれなんだけど、注意してほしいのが、先行発送グッズはライブの前に届く予定なんですけど、
And everyone, it's a bit confusing, but please note that advance-shipping merch is scheduled to arrive before the live,
受注販売グッズはライブ後！これあとなんです、受注販売グッズね。間違えないように、チェックしてください。
while order-made merch arrives after the live! Order-made merch comes later, so please check so you don't get them confused.
ぜひよろしくお願いします！
Please check them out!
詳しい情報は、公式サイト、公式X、販売サイト、そして公式特設サイトをご確認ください！告知は以上になります！
For details, please check the official site, official X, sales site, and official special site! That's all for the announcements!
と言ったことで、ソロライブはしくじらないように頑張りたいと思います！
So, I'll do my best not to screw up my solo live!
あのね、ちょっと前にさ、エイプリルフールに双子の妹登場させたりしたじゃん？
You know, a little while ago for April Fools', I introduced my twin sister, right?
なんかあいつすごい人気になっちゃったりとかしてさ。そういうね、ちょっと入れられてないしくじりとかも色々あるんですけど、
And somehow she got super popular and all. So there are various blunders like that I couldn't include, but...
ま、これからのホロライブの人生、しくじることは確実にあると思いますが、そんな天音かなたを、そして初めてのソロライブを...
well, in my Hololive life ahead, there will definitely be blunders, but please support this Amane Kanata and her first solo live...
よろしくお願いします！一緒にカートに入れたらアウト？わかんない、後でちょっと調べておくわ。みんなまた言うわ！
Thank you so much! "Out if added to the same cart?" I don't know, I'll look into it later and tell everyone!
ありがとうね！ややこしいぞ、わかる！
Thank you! It is confusing, I get it!
と言ったことでね、それじゃあみんな、またおつかなたー！ありがとう！
So with that, see you all later! Otsukanata! Thank you!
MVに飛んでくれー！やー！
Go check out the MV! Ya-!
バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!